<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
	xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
<title>Creation of a Report</title>
<section>
<para>In this tutorial, we cover the basics of how to design a report.To keep things simple, this tutorial uses a sample
      database included in the installation of Jaspersoft Studio. The data to print is retrieved using a SQL query embedded in the
      report. The first thing to do is create a new report. To do this, open the File menu, select New, and then click Jasper
      Report. A new window appears, as shown in the following figure:</para>
        		<figure>
			<title>Template selection</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="1.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="800px" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
      <para>Here you can select a template. A template defines the initial graphical layout of a report and from this dialog, in just
      a few clicks, you can create a very simple blank layout, or a much more complex one, with image, text, number of pages and so
      on. As an example, let&#39;s select a template with some elements in it. From the window displayed in the figure above,
      select Coffee and click Next. In the next step, select the folder in the workspace where you want to put the report, and name
      the new report. You can use the default folder MyReports, name the report use Example1, as shown in the following figure,
      then click Next. If you want to create a new project folder for the report, go near the end of this tutorial.</para>
             		<figure>
			<title>Folder Selection</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="2.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="800px" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
      <para>Now for the most complex part of this tutorial: the selection of a data source. The data source is the location from which
      the data is taken to fill the report. In this step, you must select a data adapter, which is essentially a connection to a
      data source. Here you have three options:</para>
 		<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
        <listitem>Selecting the data adapter &quot;One Empty Record - Empty rows&quot;: This is default data adapter used to create a
        report without any data. Can be used to define the layout of the report before connecting it to a data source. In fact, a
        data source can be provided at a later time, after the creation of the report.</listitem>
        <listitem>Selecting the data adapter &quot;Sample DB - Database JBDC Connection&quot;: This is a an SQL database used as an
        example, provided with the Jaspersoft Studio installation, for use in this tutorial.</listitem>
        <listitem>Creating a new data adapter with the &quot;New&quot; button: Jaspersoft Studio supports a wide variety of data sources.
        Using the &quot;New&quot; button allows you to browse and connect to an existing data source. Since this is a complex
        functionality, we&#39;ll address it in another tutorial.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>For this example, we will use the Sample DB, but this is not sufficent to create the report. A SQL database can contain
      many tables, with many fields, so we must specify which of these fields we will use in the report. To do this we must provide
      a SQL query that selects all the fields we want include in the report. To keep this tutorial simple, we will select all the
      fields from the table named &quot;orders&quot;. Write the query as shown in the image below and click Next.</para>
             		<figure>
			<title>Datasource Selection</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="3.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="800px" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
      <para>Using this query ensures the database will be explored and all the fields found can be added to the report. In the next
      step of the wizard there are two lists. On the left there are all the discovered fields, and on the right the ones that will
      be added to the report. At first the right list is empty, but we can move one or more elements from the left list to the
      right one using the buttons between the two lists or by double clicking on the field. An example is shown in the figure
      below:</para>
                   		<figure>
			<title>Fields Selection</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="4.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="800px" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
      <para>After selecting the fields click Next to proceed with the wizard. In the next window you can group fields. Grouping is a
      function that, for now, we will not use, so click Next. The wizard is now complete. The only thing to do is click Finish.
      Jaspersoft Studio now builds the report layout with the selected fields already included, as shown in the following
      figure:</para>
                         		<figure>
			<title>Fields Added to the Report</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="5.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="800px" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
      <para>Here, we can delete a field on the report by right-clicking on it and selecting delete, or adding a field from the Outline
      View (the tab on the bottom-left of Jaspersoft Studio). To include the value of a field in the report, drag it from the
      outline view to the design view. For example, drag a field into the detail band, a section of the report that is printed for
      each record/row in the query results. The title and the summary bands are printed just once in each report, while the page
      header and footer are printed once at the top and bottom of each page, respectively. In the figure below, see the example
      where the field SHIPREGION was removed from the report and in its palce the file SHIPCOUNTRY is added.</para>
                         		<figure>
			<title>Drag a new field</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="6.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="800px" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
      <para>When the field object is dragged inside the detail band, Jaspersoft Studio creates a text field element and sets the text
      field expression for that element to $F{SHIPNAME}. This is a simple expression to print the value of the field with the name
      SHIPNAME (the syntax $F{}). Repeat the same operation for other fields and format the text fields element by stretching,
      dragging and aligning them. It is important that the text fields are all placed inside the detail band. To add other elements
      (such lines or labels), drag them from the palette shown in the following figure into the designer view, then resize and
      arrange them as desired:</para>
                         		<figure>
			<title>Drag an Element</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="7.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="800px" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
      <para>In this case, we add a label in the title band for the report title, we add column labels using label elements placed in
      the column header band, and we place a thin line just under the text fields in the detail band. Change the height of band by
      dragging its bottom edge. A shortcut to reduce the height of the band is to double-click on its bottom edge, which aligns it
      with the bottom edge of its lowest element. You can also set properties such as the height of the band in the property sheet
      under the palette. The property sheet lets you view and edit the properties of the currently selected element in the
      designer. Click on an element in the designer or in the report inspector to select it and view its properties. For bands, you
      can also click in an unused part of the band. To preview the report, switch to the preview mode by clicking Preview in the
      designer tool bar. The preview compiles the report in the background and fills it with data retrieved by the query through
      the JDBC connection. As shown in the following figure, the detail band repeats for every row in the query results, creating a
      simple table report:</para>
                         		<figure>
			<title>Switch to Preview</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="8.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="800px" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
	</section>
</section>
