<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
	xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
<title>Creation of a Dataset</title>
<section>
        <para>Every report has a main dataset defined during its creation, that is the one used in all the previous tutorials. But
        some times we need fileds that are not returned by the query of the main dataset or the fields needed could also be in a
        different datasource. To do this we can use the element &quot;Dataset&quot;, this element permit to define many dataset
        inside the report, each one with its fields and datasource. Obviously every dataset is indipendent from the others, so its
        fields are separated from the ones of the main dataset, and also from the ones of the other datasets. With a report opened,
        to create a dataset right click on the report root node in the outline view and choose &quot;Create Dataset&quot;:</para>
      		<figure>
			<title>Select the Create Dataset Action</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="1.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="800px" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
        <para>Now a new wizard will be opened, in the first step you can select the name of the new dataset and if it use a connection
        to a datasource or it is simply empty. Since we want to read data from the databese select the first option and use as name
        &quot;GroupData&quot;, as in the image below, then hit Next.</para>
      		<figure>
			<title>Select Name and Type</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="2.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="800px" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
        <para>In the next step we have to select the data adapters of the new dataset, and since we use the same database of the main
        report even this time we will select &quot;Sample DB - Database JBDC Connection&quot;. We must also provide a query to
        retrieve the fields and this is &quot;select count(*), SHIPCITY from orders group by SHIPCITY&quot;. It returns the records
        grouped by the shipment city, in this way we have that every record read from the database with this query will contain two
        fields: the number of element for a city and the name of the city. After that we can click Next.</para>
      		<figure>
			<title>Provide the data adapter and the query</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="3.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="800px" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
        <para>At this point will be shown the fields discovered using the provided query and we can choose which add to the report.
        Since we need them all hit the button to add all and then Next, as in the following image:</para>
      		<figure>
			<title>Add the Fields</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="4.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="800px" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
        <para>At this point we can define groups, but we don&#39;t need them so hit the Finish button. The dataset will be created and
        is visible from the outline view, if you explore its element you can see that it has its own fields, variables and
        groups.</para>
     	</section>
</section>

